<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Laboratorijs on Hugo FRI website</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/</link><description>Recent content in Laboratorijs on Hugo FRI website</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><atom:link href="https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lalg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lalg/</guid><description>We conduct research in the areas of approximation and randomised algorithms, linear algebra (matrix multiplication), combinatorial optimisation (routing, problems on graphs, issues regarding the robustness of a facility location), parallel computation (algorithm mapping and scheduling, algorithms in parallel systems, hardware supported multithreading, dataflow computing), algorithm engineering and experimental algorithmics (boosting algorithm efficiency in practice), compiler design (parsing methods, attribute grammars), operating system design, grid computing (data replication on data grids), as well as computability and complexity theory.</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lui/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lui/</guid><description>The laboratory carries out research in machine learning (particularly argument based machine learning, inductive logic programming, robot learning), qualitative reasoning with robotics applications, intelligent robotics (planning, learning for planning), machine learning in medicine, and intelligent tutoring systems (ITS for programming and game playing, automated hint generation and the automatic assessment of the level of difficulty of problems for humans).</description></item><item><title>Bioinformatics Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/biolab/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/biolab/</guid><description>The laboratory carries out research in data mining, machine learning, data visualization, big data analysis and data fusion. We apply computational methods to solve practical problems and focus on systems biology, biomedicine and natural sciences. The laboratory is developing Orange, a comprehensive suite that joins machine learning and visual programming, and collaborates in development of cool interactive web-based data exploration platforms like dictyExpress.</description></item><item><title>Computer Communications Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrk/</guid><description>Our research is focused on communication networks and protocols, cloud architectures and services, cloud and network security, virtualization, ICT sustainability, computer supported learning systems and the use of agile methodologies. We have researched the orchestration of complex virtual environments, container orchestration, examined SDN and NFV and their use in cloud environments, and developed our own virtual cloud laboratory. Our latest project focuses on carrier-grade cloud solutions for large telco providers.</description></item><item><title>Computer Structures and Systems Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrss/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrss/</guid><description>The laboratory is focused on the computational methods for modelling, simulation and analysis of fundamentally different system families. We are interested in computational approaches in systems and synthetic biology, the analysis of coordinated behaviour in biological systems, the design of quantum-dot cellular automata processing structures, and the understanding of human behaviour through the analysis of mobile sensing data. The laboratory therefore consists of four groups, the Computational Biology Group, the Collective Behaviour Group, the Quantum-dot Cellular Automata group and the Mobile Computing Group.</description></item><item><title>Computer Vision Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lrv/</guid><description>We research the capture, processing and interpretation of 2D and 3D visual data, machine learning in computer vision, and the use of images in computer-human interactions. We work in the following specific areas: interactive visual signage systems, 3D documentation in archaeology and cultural heritage, interpretation of images in biometry, medicine, geology and meteorology, the forensic analysis of images and video, virtual and augmented reality, as well as in the production of computer games and in new media art installations (in cooperation with the Academy of Fine Arts).</description></item><item><title>Information Systems Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/li/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/li/</guid><description>The focus of the research here includes software development methodologies and business process evaluation. We offer efficient approaches to the evaluation of information systems, specific information solutions and specific IT related processes. The approaches break down IT products or IT processes into key elements and evaluate them through a comprehensive set of criteria. We have excellent references in the areas of information system strategic planning and context aware applications, where we have developed a context engine prototype.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Adaptive Systems and Parallel Processing</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/laspp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/laspp/</guid><description>Our main research topics include development of adaptive algorithms in areas of artificial neural networks, data clustering, data mining, information-theoretic modelling and reinforcement learning, and design of computer systems, ranging from high performance computing to on-chip designs. We are mainly focused on problems where the lack of theoretical knowledge prevents exact solutions and where special software and hardware are demanded for efficient processing. We are also involved in digital logic design of arithmetic circuits, processing on GPUs, and smart wireless sensor networks.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Architecture and Signal Processing</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/laps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/laps/</guid><description>None</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Biomedical Computer Systems and Imaging</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lbrso/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lbrso/</guid><description>The laboratory conducts research in the field of biomedical signal and imaging data. Our research includes describing physiological phenomena, modelling physiologic relationships, graphically displaying anatomic details and physiologic functions, visualising biomedical signals, developing standardised databases, developing detection and recognition techniques, evaluating the performance of recognition techniques, analysing bioelectric patterns, and developing performance measures and protocols, biomedical information technologies and software.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Cognitive Modeling</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lkm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lkm/</guid><description>The laboratory apursuesresearch in machine learning, neural networks, statistics, image, text and data mining. Recent research has been related to the generation of semi-artificial data, the analysis of big data with the MapReduce approach, evaluating the reliability of single models’ predictions, text summarisation using archetypal analysis, web-user profiling, applying evolutionary computation to data mining, spatial data mining with multi-level directed graphs, bottom-up inductive logic programming, heuristic search methods in clickstream mining, multi-view learning, mining of heterogeneous networks and e-learning.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Cryptography and Computer Security</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lkrv/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lkrv/</guid><description>We focus on cryptography and computer security, discrete mathematics, coding theory and statistical design. We have extensive experience in applied cryptography, especially public key cryptosystems (elliptic curve cryptosystems), cryptographic protocols (AKC) and their implementations in restricted environments, such as smart cards (including HSM and FPGA). We also study algebraic combinatorics (distance-regular graphs, association schemes, finite geometries, codes, finite fields and the like), probability and statistics.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Data Technologies</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lpt/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lpt/</guid><description>Areas of interest include data acquisition, management, integration, analysis and visualisation, all within the framework of information system development, management and governance. Special interest is devoted to internet of things, big data, real-time data management, the analysis of large networks, data streams, information extraction, etc. We work closely with industry partners in developing and testing new technologies and approaches.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Integration of Information Systems</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/liis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/liis/</guid><description>The laboratory has established strong foundation in service computing, cloud computing, digital transformation and conducts research in the field of the integration and interoperability of applications, cloud-native architectures, microservices and APIs, devices, information systems, architectures and platforms. We focus on software architectures, platforms, design patterns. We work on technologies for the execution, monitoring and optimization of business processes and on IoT integration and mobility issues, including novel localization, authentication and gait analysis algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Mathematical Methods in Computer and Information Science</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lmmri/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lmmri/</guid><description>We are involved in research in various spheres of continuous and discrete mathematics. On the one hand our research topics include commutative algebra, linear algebra, nonlinear dynamical systems, Brownian motion, martingales, algebraic topology, computational topology, topological data analysis and scientific computing. On the discrete side of the mathematical spectrum, however, we deal with problems in graph theory, particular the structural and colouring problems of graphs, which are also connected with problems in computational geometry.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory for Ubiquitous systems</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lusy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lusy/</guid><description>The prime area of research interest is efficient data handling in distributed pervasive environments, which store terabytes of data that present a challenge in at least two areas: the efficient storage and handling of the data. The distributed environment is inherently capable of parallel processing and requires a proper data and work distribution. Our research is concentrated on three areas: unstructured text handling, data deduplication and on-line streaming data processing. We are also active in the area of Computer Science Education.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory of Computer Graphics and Multimedia</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lgm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lgm/</guid><description>The laboratory performs R&amp;amp;D in the fields of multimedia technologies, human-computer interaction and computer graphics. Our main focus is on audio processing and music information retrieval (audio understanding, organization of music archives), interactive 3D visualization (medical imaging, games, VR/AR), and e-Learning (learning for people with disabilities, gamification). We have extensive experience in developing software solutions for desktop, mobile and cloud platforms and are active in the development of visualizations, interactive learning systems, and didactic games.</description></item><item><title>Laboratory of e-media</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/lem/</guid><description>The laboratory focuses on advanced (lightweight) communications (e.g. the Internet of Things), security, privacy, e-business, and human factor modelling. Our research devotes particular attention to the analysis and design of advanced systems (from PKI to critical infrastructures), cryptographic protocols, advanced security and privacy analytics (e.g., big data methods for searching for precursory signals), and the quantitative treatment of the human factor. We have patented lightweight cryptographic protocols and developed practical (industry relevant) food supply chain management solutions based on RFIDs.</description></item><item><title>Software Engineering Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/ltpo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/ltpo/</guid><description>The laboratory is involved in teaching and research in the areas of software engineering and information systems, with an emphasis on agile software development methods (i.e. factors affecting successful adoption, agile project management, performance evaluation, the introduction of lean concepts, and similar), graph grammars and graph algorithms (parsing graph grammars, etc.), model driven development (reverse engineering, domain specific languages), and web data mining (stochastic models for user behaviour analysis, separating interleaved web sessions, etc.</description></item><item><title>Visual Cognitive Systems Laboratory</title><link>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/luvss/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www-hugo.netlify.com/en/laboratorij/luvss/</guid><description>The laboratory is involved in basic and applied research of visually enabled intelligent systems. We have extensive experience with visual object tracking, object detection and categorization, incremental visual learning, as well as with systems for human-robot interactive learning and the development of computer vision solutions for smart mobile devices. Our experience has been accumulated in collaboration with a variety of research partners in a number of the EU, national and industry funded projects which address these research issues.</description></item></channel></rss>